Hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights. Today I have
the great pleasure of speaking to Alex
Kiefer.
Alex is currently the senior research
and design engineer at Versus but was
pre- previously a lecturer at Monash
University in philosophy.
His work is deeply exciting and unique
and focuses on the convergence of
machine learning, computational
neuroscience and philosophy of mind.
Which Alex, I'm sure you know some of my
favorite topics. The latter one I feel a
little bit more well versed on but I
can't wait to learn more from you about
the the two prior.
Um
Firstly, thank you so much for joining
me. This is really exciting. I think I
think you know, reading over your work
both prior to the kind of research I did
for this and and during
I found it to be incredibly as I say
unique and special because I feel like
you're one of a kind in so far as not
many people are really being really able
to merge the mathematical side and the
philosophical side. So I'm actually just
curious more generally about how you got
into this convergence point. Was it
through maths and uh machine learning or
was it more through philosophy and then
you had to add the maths on top of that?
Yeah, well, first of all, thanks so much
for uh
for talking with me. Like I'm looking
forward to just discussing with you and
it's nice that it also happens to be on
a public uh
podcast.
Absolutely.
Um so so yeah, that's it's a good
question. Uh
So I I came from a philosophy
actually originally came from an art of
fine arts background. So I'm I I have a
tendency to go from one thing to another
but I got into all of this through
philosophy. So I would say as a
philosophy grad- graduate student, I was
thinking about cognitive architecture,
you know, in a naive way. I was starting
to think about these things. And this
was
um you know, this was this was some time
ago. So I'd say the landscape was a bit
different. So, not every philosophy
graduate student would necessarily have
been exposed to like deep learning
connectionism. Indeed, when I was
working on my PhD, deep learning was
just starting to sort of be a a thing.
Uh
so
So, I started to I started to um find
references to like connectionist models
for things like natural language
processing.
Uh and I got interested in those things.
Um
and I'd say I mean uh
as is the case for many people in in in
my field um
Andy Clark's um EBS article, Whatever
Next, big watershed moment, where I had
I had been thinking about um for example
um
higher-order Bayesian um Bayesian models
uh signal detection theory of
consciousness for example by people like
Hakwan Lau. Um so, I've been thinking in
these terms of generative models
already, uh but then that article really
just sort of
caused some things to click into place
for me. Um and I'd had sort of a um
I don't know, immature or casual
interest in um software development,
coding on the side, and mathematics. Um
so, essentially
I got into this through philosophy. I
picked up as much mathematics as I could
off on on the street, as it were, uh to
do the things I wanted to do. And I just
thought it was really essential to be
able to build some of these models to
understand really what the hell was
going on, right? So,
if
uh not not to not to get too far into
this topic yet, but um
I mean uh
part of my philosophical point of view
is um is that really a naive sort of uh
atomistic symbolic approach to content
uh the content of mental representations
or representations in general is not
really um
uh is not really the way to go, although
it's it's sort of um maybe predominant,
I'd say, in a lot of the philosophical
literature. So,
um to really understand something, I
think you have to understand its
functional profile. And so, I I I
thought that there were a lot of
discussions in philosophy about
cognitive architecture that were not
sufficiently grounded in
a kind of knowledge of the way that
these representations might work, which
I think to some extent, I mean, there's
always sort of the low road and the high
road, right? There's always top-down
understanding and more bottom-up
understanding, but I think some
bottom-up understanding I felt was
necessary to to understand this this
stuff. And then, of course, once you
start to work with models like this,
they
sort of become interesting to work on
their in their own right. So, to some
extent, I was pulled away from the more
purely theoretical questions into
wanting to build better models of
cognition.
Sure. Well, I mean, it's in the most
praise you know, praising way possible
you wouldn't be able to tell. That's why
I had to ask the question.
I mean, again, I'm not a mathematician,
so I can't you know, I can't say I can't
be an authority
on your mathematical chops, but
honestly, it's um
I've always I've always sort of
considered you a philosopher and then I
you know, reread the papers I was like,
"Wow." Some of this is like super
technical.
I was really really impressed. So, no, I
find it very I find it very admirable
when philosophers cuz I guess it's a
path that I'm also you know, to be
candid also trying to pursue, which is
supplementing or combining theoretical
thinking with
you know, with mathematical modeling or
mathematical formalisms. So, it's it's
kind of nice to you and people like
Maxwell pave that pave that way. So,
thanks in a weird kind of indirect way.
I'm so glad you brought up content and
representation cuz that's actually
exactly where I wanted to start.
I kind of thought we would start
somewhat broadly.
So,
I guess
it's funny, you know, doing a psychology
master's, you probably hear the word
representation quite a lot and I did,
but no one ever takes no one ever really
goes deeper than that. It's like, "Okay,
there are representations and we you
kind of have a hunch about what that
means." and we think about paintings or
photographs, and they stand for
something.
However, just doing this podcast and and
doing more reading, you kind of see that
it's actually an incredibly contentious
issue what a representation is,
do we have representations in the brain,
mind, uh and so on.
I was I I feel like I'd
come across notions of um similarity and
resemblance in the representational
literature, but maybe not as sort of
directly explicated by yourself.
You sort of speak about a form of
Bayesian structural representationism.
I thought this was a really, really
interesting idea, because as you know
and as you recognize,
in philosophy,
resemblance or similarity and
representation are often divorced. Um
people will say, "Well, you can't get
representation out of resemblance."
Something a akin to that. How do you
manage to get representationism out of
sort of structural similarity?
Uh
and you know, what do your what does
your position entail more broadly?
Yeah. Um
So,
so indeed, I think representation is
something that it's it's a a term that a
lot of people across many fields use,
and
you know, I think they're justified in
using it. It's it's a it's a fairly easy
language game to pick up in a way to
start talking about representations. Um
And I think I think the term has just
has just proven its usefulness just in
the the fruitfulness of all the various
um
research programs that have been that
that employ this as a central term.
Um
And so, I guess I guess to start with
your direct question, um
I think one one So, right, so how do you
get how do you get past the normal the
usual objections to basing um an account
of representation, a philosophical
theory of representation in resemblance?
Um I guess the I guess the the maybe the
first objection that you might encounter
is, well,
resemblance is all over the place.
Um it's a very cheap. Um whereas
representation, especially in the sense
that's relevant to psychological
capacities and theorizing about those
capacities
should be something more special. So I'd
say the first move to make is to say
that representation is also cheap. That
that is to argue that so I actually have
a
I'll probably say this a lot.
I I say it in any case enough in
conversations. I have a paper on this. I
haven't published.
But this
sort
of against inflationary concepts of
mental representation. So I think there
are some danger you know, not dangerous.
There are some waters you get into here
flirting with things like panpsychism
that maybe we can touch on at some
point. But
I think
I think here here here's my view. If if
you can come up with a serviceable
notion of representation
that plays the that does the explanatory
work it should both with respect to
cognitive science and also also in
common sense terms with respect to like
capturing the manifest image as well as
the scientific image. Right? If you can
sort of understand how this this thing
that you're calling representation does
those jobs.
And if it turns out that it's
everywhere, well, then it's everywhere.
Right? So I don't think there's any need
to front-load the assumption that
representation needs to be rare.
So that's that's what now I don't want
to say that every resemblance relation
is a representation relation. But I
think you can part of the answer to to
that objection is to bite the bullet and
say
you know, individual neurons probably
represent things for example.
In the in the same sense in the same
fundamental sense as you or I do at the
personal level. Maybe with different
features within that right within that
category.
But we still get the extra step. Right?
So we still get the extra step from pure
resemblance to in your in your work at
least I mean some people would just say
there are you know, at least in basic
minds there are no representations. And
here I'm thinking about the sort of
radical and activist who says any
president is kind of scaffolded
non-basic minds or basic forms of mind.
Uh but you do want to positive
representations as you said and
and you do make it clear that we have to
go beyond resemblance. So maybe what I'm
kind of leading you here is is towards
the kind of teleosemantics
or kind of more functional semantics. I
really enjoy I mean I personally really
really like this idea um that in some
ways a representation means something to
the organism.
I guess cuz it for me it feeds into
ideas of um
sense making or affordances or whatever
you want to call it. So how do we go
from pure
objective in  marks re-
resemblances to
a representation that is for or realized
within an organism.
Yeah. So
all right. So I'm going to try to spell
this out. This is difficult cuz to me
this is like in a way it's the closest
to the core the very core philosophical
problems that I think remain sort of
unresolved or without a uh uncontentious
resolution resolution for good reason
cuz cuz it relates to basically the way
in which the sort of subject relates to
the object or the mind relates to the
world. So this is the caveat that this
is still an ongoing um I I don't feel
settled about about some of these
questions.
Um
what what what Yakov
uh Hooven and I said in that in in our
papers on this
um is that
um
it following more or less the account
that had been in the literature um is
that
you need not just structural resemblance
in order to have a representation but
exploitable structural resemblance.
Um but I do want to I do want to
emphasize that um
I and I can to some degree speak speak
for Yakov since we collaborated on this
but you know he has his own views.
Um so I'll just speak for myself for
now. Um
I I don't see either the resemblance
relation or the exploitability relation
as necessarily
in fact relations to concrete
particulars external to the organism.
Let's start with resemblance. So in this
this is this is in the papers that we
wrote
although it could stand to be made more
explicit I think.
The
fundamentally the kind of resemblance I
think that the account rests on is
resemblance between the structure of
your internal model
and some hypothetical world.
And it needn't be the actual world. So
what you represent in the first instance
and this this sort of resonates with
some of the things that were said early
on in the
Bayesian brain as the Bayesian brain
idea started to break across philosophy
and cognitive science about
um
you know your representation of the
world being something like an internal
simulation or a perception is like
vertical hallucination or online control
hallucination.
So
so the resemblance in the first instance
I would say is between the internal
cognitive structures and a hypothetical
world which may or may not
match the actual world. And then I would
say a similar thing about
exploitability.
Um
exploitability you might try to catch
that catch that out in very obviously
naturalistic terms in terms of like as
you said teleology. What is the function
of this cognitive structure? What does
it tend to allow me to achieve or what's
what did it evolve to allow me to
achieve for example? I am definitely not
a teleosemanticist actually. I think
there's been a lot of good efforts to
integrate active inference and
teleosemantics in the literature. I I
think we can get into this if you like
but I think it's a I think it's a
misstep. I don't think you should have
to look at least if you interpret
teleology in terms of
something historical. I think it's a
misstep. I don't think you need to look
to
any kind of evolutionary history or
beyond the current functioning of the
organism in order to say what it's the
contents of its states are.
That was already a mouthful. I can
always go on, but
Well, there's there's plenty there. So,
I guess the first thing I want to just
touch on is
So, yeah, you do speak about the sort of
structural resemblance between And And
this is actually, as you say, quite, at
least in my eyes,
well-established within the literature
that the the the structural resemblance
between the Bayesian generative model
and the generative process. I really
like your addition there that doesn't
have to be the real world because you've
got imagination, memory, dreams, and so
on. And
I have had conversations with people who
say that I think, you know,
the perception-action cycle itself
needs to be maybe buttressed by uh
either retrospective or prospective ways
of thinking. And that's actually kind of
in the phenomenology as well, right?
Husserl distinguishing between the lived
moment and then also
retrospection and prospection more
formally.
So, that's a really nice addition.
What
What is maybe slightly more contentious
is if we fold truth conditions in
uh
or satisfaction conditions. And
I I feel like
again, I don't want to speak for you,
you can tell me, that if the generative
model is meant to accurately map onto
the generative process in a way that
minimizes that KL divergence,
there has to be some element of truth
tracking or
uh
we can't be completely making it up on
the spot because then our models are
basically useless over time.
So, how much do you then fold not only
uh
the the real-time exploitation, but also
the fact that there's got there's some
truth relation between uh world and
model?
Yeah. So, so I think on the fundamental
um again, uh
if you just want to characterize what
about this thing makes it a
representation,
I think it does
I I tend to think in terms of truth
conditions. I actually think truth
conditions are nice fit with a Bayesian
approach because what are distributions
over like events, right?
And they you can think of these as
events and and their descriptions of
states of affairs. Not it's not like
your distribution is over a dog, right?
It's over there is a dog. So
it's a it's a nice fit and of course you
can think of um
of um
well, there there are nice relationships
between logic as usually defined over
propositions with truth values and
probability theory. So
I think that all works out very nicely.
Um
So
I guess the question is to what I mean
practically speaking your your model and
this is sort of a very free energy
principle type statement. I mean your
model your model will not exist if it
doesn't track the truth to some degree.
And I actually I know there's a there's
a there's definitely a pushback in the
free energy principle and active
inference literature against the idea
that these models have to be veridical
because they're used for control of
course as well.
Um but I think I think that the clear
truth is that the your your of course so
perfect veridicality
at least at the sort of
uh
highest possible like
um resolution or fidelity of
representation is is not needed and is
probably would be counterproductive,
right? You don't want the map to be as
rich as the territory usually.
But I also think you can't
you absolutely need to to track the
truth to some degree and the nice thing
about structural resemblance approaches
is that you can
you can
quantify various ways of doing it, but
you can try to quantify the degree of
structural resemblance and then you
don't have to talk about just like truth
or falsity. This is something that can
come in degrees.
Sure. Okay, so that's that we're kind of
in agreement that there's there's only a
slight it's not a caveat. It's a kind of
red herring I'm sure that we you skirt.
It's actually something I raised with
Carl
in our first conversation that I haven't
raised since because uh you kind of get
you kind of get integrated into the
Bayesian game and then you forget all of
your sort of actually quite useful naive
questions.
You know, I asked him
what happens if there is just like no
noumenon, right? What happens if there
just are no hidden states? If I just
take a very kind of George Berkeley
idealist position. There's no kind of
All there are ideas. I mean, I guess you
could posit the ideas as being the
latent states and and they're appearance
as being the sensory you know, input.
But
it it's
it's a kind of classical philosophical
question which is what happens if we're
a brain in the vat? Do we still get
truth conditions out of that? Is can we
say that, you know, we've got
hierarchies of observation and what they
track even within a kind of illusory
space?
Mhm.
Yeah, I love that I love that question.
Um
I So
Okay, I mean, there's different layers
of this. There's different ways of
thinking about these skeptical
scenarios, but um
I would say that you still have truth
conditions for for sure to the extent
that
I mean, to some to some degree I'm just
like an intuitive internalist or you
know, not a solipsist, right? But
internalist. I start from the internal
Cartesian kind of point of view and um
I do think there's something sort of
esoteric, you might say, about the way
we represent the world. Like it seems it
seems as though to me uh that I perceive
things as being thus and so. There's
sort of a right? And the condition for
that being true, I I I think that that
So that representation has a truth
condition.
Um whether or not of course whether or
not it's true or could be true. Whether
or not the structure of the universe is
such as to, you know,
to be true.
Uh even possibly. Um
I do think uh
with respect to any skeptical
there might be versions of skepticism
where you say there's literally just
nothing out there.
And um I'm not quite sure what to say
about that, but I have thought more
about um so David Chalmers has this
great paper called I think it's called
the Matrix as Metaphysics uh where he
goes into
some of these issues and
um I don't know if I'll be able to fully
justify this at the moment, but I know
that where I've landed on this thinking
about the stuff in the past is that um
from the point of view of trying to
model the generative process, right? So
you figure every agent has its own sort
of subjective ontology, which is part of
this is an aspect of this internal
simulation that you develop over time
through sensory feedback. Um now
whatever
the nature of the the noumenon is
um
it's something
that um through interacting with it
has allowed you to generate these
structures.
Uh and I think those structures
um
those structures
I guess is a form of structural realism,
right? So the the struct exist um
regardless of whether even if we're in a
simulation, um
Yeah.
there's a sense in which
the internal representations that I have
their truth conditions would be
satisfied un- unless, right? So so it
could be part of your overall model that
you say and this isn't a computer
simulation or or something, right? So so
these very high-level um sort of
beliefs about the kind of world you live
in, your metaphysical beliefs might
might uh falsify your um your overall
model or not. Um but you could be
agnostic on those points.
Sure. Yeah, I mean I think Yablo
actually has a really nice contribution
to here in his um How to Entrain Your
Evil Demon paper, which is that
like the demon is giving us pretty
reliable, uh
you know, pretty reliable signals.
Whether it's tricking us or not, I mean
we we you know, there's kind of
beautiful sensory motor loop whereby we
move and what we sense is changed by
what we how we move and how we move is
changed by what we sense and we seem to
have quite good control over our evil
demon. I guess like as just a kind of
budding philosopher you always run that
argument to the ground which is that
maybe there is no you know maybe there
is no simulation there just is
pure awareness.
Right? Um
Or there's just
Or there's just you
or well not you but you you know your
mind and you're a solipsist
and in that case
there is nothing to track. It's not like
a computer simulation there you
mentioned David Chalmers he's writing
this work on virtual reality which I'm
sure you've checked out and he you know
he doesn't think there's such he doesn't
think it really matters, right? Like it
the the same structures the same
philosophical relations still hold
whether it's
carbon or silicon or but whatever.
But there's still this kind of binary
distinction. Okay, you got what is
mapping or the generative proce- the
generative model and the generative
process that which is being mapped.
And
I just think there is at least
philosophically I might be wrong here a
skeptical position where you just go
well maybe there just is
the you know the sense of mapping but
there's actually nothing behind that,
right? Like all there is is the map.
There is no territory.
The I'd say
yeah so
even the sort of thin sort of realism
you get out of this David Chalmers
perspective might be sunk if it's like
I forget what this
Russell called it but basically the the
the hypothesis that the world sprang
into existence
a second ago, right? And all your
memories with the all your memories
intact.
Yeah, but it's it's Bertrand Russell,
right? Did he
Believe so.
Maybe Russell, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah so yeah so I don't have an answer
to that.
I don't think there
I
In general though I think um
yeah so so skepticism is something that
indeed you have to you have to kind of
struggle with it I I guess as an
advocate if you study philosophy in that
way, but I
I think to me the the the outcome of
that struggle is a
just a realization
that that's the way things are
and and that's okay.
Um
Yeah.
It's not really okay, right? Cuz if you
actually found out that these scenarios
were true and you suddenly woke up and
you're in a completely different world,
okay, that would be that would be quite
traumatic traumatizing, but
Well, so would be being alone in the
universe, you know, that would be quite
traumatic as well.
Honestly, it's it's yes. Um it in most
moods it's easy to dismiss, but if
you're if you take it seriously,
honestly that could be one of that's
that's one of the most terrifying
prospects I think, but let's acknowledge
it rather than um
um trying to dismiss it via a um you
know, superficial argument.
Sure. Sure. I think in part this is a we
don't have to go into this, but this is
in part a result of philosophical
education at least in the Anglo-Saxon
world, which is they start you basically
on skepticism.
Um they start you on Descartes and then
you read
the stuff in active inference about
perception and they're all saying, well,
we kind of take direct realism as you
know, for granted and you're like, what?
Like we all like at school we said that
was rubbish.
Um
I just wonder and and then you know, you
start hearing all the externalist
attacks on internalism. So I'm kind of
curious about your experience
openly and it sounds like it's a taboo
and it really ought not to be and I
don't think it is, but openly or
promulgating or proposing a internalist
position. It seems to me at least that
from the outside
a fairly rare position to occupy and the
kind of hot thing is to be as
externalist as possible. Albeit there is
some pushback of course against radical
and activism. So I'm just curious about
sort of sociologically how you found
that.
Yeah, no, I was absolutely it's been
it's definitely sort of a um
unpopular position within
within sort of this this this
well, I'd say in general as you said in
general these days. Um so So, right. So,
before I ever got into the active
inference stuff,
um
I I I sort of was already fighting the
tide against I'd say externalism.
To me it's just
it it's a perfectly legitimate set of
motivations, right? That that motivate
the externalists, right? I want to
understand the role that representation
and related notions play in like
explanations in cognitive science. And
that's a sort of third-person sort of
operation and uh
you know, uh and so you want to like on
on what basis would I posit contents?
Well, I'm trying to explain
you know, how this mouse manages to
navigate in its environment or whatever.
Um and there's no reason not to use um
sort of external externalists um
uh
externally available evidence in in
doing that. Um so it So, that's fine.
That's about content ascription. But I I
think um
I don't know. I think So, so that that
movement I I'm not sure exactly where
the roots begin. They probably go back
as far as anything, but um there were
these moments in I guess the '70s the in
the '80s people like Tyler Burge were
really pushing anti-individualism
uh in the philosophy of psychology. Um
and I think this is just one of those
cases where the sort of the baby got
thrown out with the bathwater or things
this is like a you know, a pendulum and
I think the pendulum swung very far in
in direction of externalism, but I just
I just think that leaves out um
some very very basic points like the
fact that what we're trying to explain I
I would think and maybe this is too tied
to consciousness. I'm curious what you
think about that, but
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I'm trying to explain an organism's
point of view on the world.
So, I think you want to limit yourself
to
to that. And if you start to legislate
about what the organism's point of view
on the world is by
um
reading in information about what you
know is in their environment, but you
don't know how they're parsing it or how
they're processing the information into
cognitive internal structures, I think
you're in danger of um
um sort of just biasing your account of
what they of what their point of view by
your point of view. And um that's a sort
of naive way of putting it, but I think
you can make some of that more more
precise.
I Well, yeah, I think I Yeah, I don't
know how much we need to I think we're
kind of we we're singing from the same
hymn sheet here. I think um I mean, I
think I'm in quite a privileged position
actually as a relative layman because I
have no skin in the game, right? I just
see things as I see it in terms of my
intuitions.
And I think also starting from
consciousness and privileging
consciousness, privileging it lived
experience,
at least biases you towards some form of
internalism. I mean, I had this
conversation with Inez, Inez Apolito in
one of the earliest episodes of this
um series.
And you know, I I'm exactly like you. I
mean, I read Evan Thompson and I read
Varela and I love it. I actually think
it's really beautiful. And I love this
idea of the sensory motor loop. And Evan
Thompson actually in Mind in Life talks
about how
the mind-body problem can be become a
body-body problem. It's the lived body
versus the living body.
But even if you read that chapter on
consciousness, and that Evan, I'm sure
would say this, I'm sure they'll say it
in the actual book, you don't get You
still don't get the phenomenal state You
don't get the phenomenal reality.
Right? You still have that distance. And
it's same thing I say with Inez, which
is that well,
I'm very happy to say that um
affordances are socially structured by
our language, by our culture, and so on.
But like
there's still something it is like for
something to afford itself to me.
And I just I have a real hard time
saying that way of seeing the world is
is relative. It's in some
Wittgensteinian way. The qualia is a
kind of old-fashioned idea and let's
throw it out.
It just doesn't do the job for me. Um
I've had
a bit of a I had a very small chat with
Yiannis about this and I think we're
both on the same page which is that
No, well actually and to be fair I just
don't think anyone's going to be a
really true strong illusionist about the
hard problem and and about
consciousness. Now you can get into your
key Frankish and Dan Dennett and say
well it's about qualia and postulating
these private states and again I'm not
really well versed enough to understand
that.
But I think you're absolutely right.
Starting from philosophy of mind
analytic philosophy of mind in the
tradition
makes one very
very skeptical at least of
reductive
um a reductive account.
Which I guess is actually also you know
sorry for rambling it's it's also kind
of weird because then you see some very
strong externalists also push back
against uh
reductivism. As I was talking to Julian
Kiverstein and Julian is very unhappy
with the idea that neural states are
you.
And Evan says this as well. But they
think that well actually you can just
expand that notion into your sensory
motor capacities and your affordances
with the environment. I'm like no you're
you're still missing something.
Like you're missing phenomenal reality.
So I'm kind of curious about what you
think about that. Like where where
is it do we get out of the problem by
saying you know neurons aren't you but
actually if you talk about your wider
socio-cultural
uh you know contexts and your history we
get you.
Or or do we need to fold in
phenomenality?
Yeah, so
I think there are a couple of issues
here. Um so so one strand of this leads
right into some other work I've done
that the psychophysical identity stuff
um where so I think
so the the sort of um
representationalist versus an activist
axis is one thing and certainly I fall
on the representationalist end of that
and I have to admit I probably need to
give an activist their due and and try
to really
really immerse myself in the core
literature there but but to me it's just
it's a non-starter. I don't see how you
can explain
just
perceptual errors and things like that
without appealing to something that says
that the world is this way even though
it's not and and to me that's already
sufficient to be a representation and
and I don't encounter many super radical
and activists who think that we don't
need representations. So
once you have representations in play
then
that's that's all I've ever I've ever
assumed.
Um so I don't worry about too much about
that but then you're also talking about
sort of the
I guess the issue of whether the
phenomenal can be reduced to the
physical
um things like that and so in in the
psychophysical identity paper I
and I'm not sure by the way of course I
don't as a Bayesian philosopher I don't
have settled views
quite generally but the view that I
explore in that paper and that I do
still want to pursue as a serious
possibility
is that you can have something like a
like a mind brain identity thesis. So to
me that
whatever it is it has to do justice to
phenomenology.
Yeah.
Um
so if we even if it's that you're just
your neurons which I I don't think
that's quite the story. I think probably
the scientific account coming from the
the life sciences it is and um and
physics and so on is not is not finished
yet and I think wherever we end up with
that I don't I think it'll it'll make it
sound less absurd whatever it is. It's
not going to be that we're a collection
of neurons necessarily. It's probably
some some form of self-organization um
that that has a sort of natural unity.
We can get into that but but essentially
um
you'll have that will
even if that's true we I I think a
satisfying account has to be able to
explain
um in completely compelling terms
um
w- why it
how how that could be true, right? So,
how could my current experience of the
world while looking at my screen right
now
uh talking to you
how how the hell could that be the same
thing as a bunch of, you know, neuronal
activity and so on. And I don't
personally think that applying to my
wider
ecological niche or anything like that
is going to help elucidate that.
Right.
I think it's it's more like we need to
elucidate the connection between the
physical mechanisms the physical
mechanism is actually um is actually
stacking the deck too much. The physical
processes
and my conscious experience. And I think
there's some hope that we can do that.
Mhm.
But it it cuts along very different
lines from the enactivist kind of
solution.
Yeah. Well, again, I
I just personally think that that
concession is made at least within a lot
of enactivism. Even sort of um like Alva
Noë's sensory motor theory
talks about how
sort of neural signatures will tell you
maybe why you're seeing red rather than
blue
or why you're hearing rather than
seeing, but it doesn't tell you why
you're hearing. Right? It doesn't tell
you why you're seeing red. Yeah, I I
like your optimism. Um
I don't know if I share it if about the
about the relationship between the
physical and the phenomenal.
Uh but I have a soft I have a sort of uh
um
a soft appreciation, let's say, for
more esoteric theories of consciousness,
whether that be a kind of conscious
realism ala Donald Hoffman or maybe even
panpsychism. But again, I've got no
commitments. Um
We'll we'll loop back, but I actually
wanted to just quickly touch upon this
notion of teleosemantics
um
which was new to me until a couple of
months ago, and then I got into I was
reading about teleosemantics and
teleosemiotics and the difference
between those. But if we just stick with
teleosemantics, the idea being that sort
of from
a what tellos, purpose, a biological
function, let's say, you can get
representation, you can get some
meaning.
And you want to push back on that in a
way because of the historicity. So, the
content,
um, itself is not necessarily determined
by your
background.
It's interesting because I kind of see I
I kind of see it differently, although I
don't necessarily I don't necessarily
have a good way of articulating it, only
because
we take as an assumption that the prior
preferences we have in our active
inference models are
at least constituted in part by
evolutionary priors.
And I presume that my representation and
then it's also coming from the
affordance,
uh, literature, you know, my
representation of a table is very
different from an ant's representation
of a table because the affordance is the
difference. So, what do you mean in
terms of, um,
siphoning off the evolutionary history
from some form of teleosemantics?
Yeah. Oh, great. So, I mean, first I
should say I think teleosemantics is an
amazing research program. Like, I've
read a lot of Ruth Millikan's work,
which is foundational to it, and it's
fantastic work, absolutely foundational
to where we are today. Um, but I think I
mean, the big picture is that I just
think as Okay, I'll I'll answer the
question you asked, which is what do I
mean by siphoning off the evolutionary
history, but
just quickly to motivate why I want to
do that, um, I think you have to bite
some bullets. So, I'm willing to bite
the representation is everywhere bullet.
But, one one thing that Millikan
explicitly says is, so if you have, you
know, there's these thought experiments
like I think it's called Swamp Man or
something where some some creature
appears suddenly out of out of some
quantum fluctuation or something,
and is identical to a,
uh, physically identical to a human
being who would have evolved over
millions of years, et cetera, right? To
have the same structure. Uh, um,
what Millikan says is that basically the
the internal structures of that
creature,
um
such as the heart, brain, whatever, um
shouldn't really even be called that
because those right, those terms refer
to things that have a certain function
and that function comes from the
selection history. So, I guess the idea
is, well, this thing just appeared, you
don't really know what its parts are
for. You don't really know what anything
is for. And I just completely reject
that intuition. I think it's clear that
if you
you know, you might have to spend a
couple minutes analyzing it, but if you
were talking to to it depend as the case
may be, but you know, you'll you'll see
you'll be able to figure out what these
things are for. It's like, well, its
heart, the purpose of its heart is to
pump blood in the sense that it's doing
that now and it's keeping it alive, and
I don't think you need to look further
back. Um
but and and so I guess I guess that does
start to get into
what I mean by by separating these
things off. So, I think if you have
if you have a rich enough account of the
current functional organization of
something, that you should be able to
figure out
there's a sense in which you can cash
out uh the
the purpose of
the structures within that thing without
knowing about the history. So, maybe I'm
relying here on on an overly um
complacent distinction between like
constitutive and causal um
relationships. So, like certainly the
history is necessary to understand how
this structure got to exist. I just
think that's a different question from
like
what is it doing now? Possibly what's
its purpose now? Certainly what's its
content. So, I want to add one more
remark here, which is
even if you had um a nice way of cashing
out
biological function, um
let's say you could even do it in a way
that doesn't appeal to history, I still
don't think that that's even the same
thing. I don't think that's the what you
want to explain semantic normativity. I
just think it's a different kind of
question.
Yes. Yes. And in fact, that's
interestingly the very point that Hutto
and Myin make in rejecting
teleosemantics, which is that like
you're how you gain content out of
biological necessity. And I think Jerry
Fodor had a similar stance. Um
Yeah, I also wonder whether we need to
make a distinction between what I can
say about the swamp creature.
Um what it is like to be the swamp
creature. In terms of maybe it's not
necessary for me to know the entire
evolutionary past of the swamp creature
in some deep epistemological ways to
account or or to make a rough
approximation of what's going on.
But as you say, in terms of the actual
ontological status of its internal
states. And by that I mean
I I
I I I buy the thing about heart and
lungs because you can get those by
analogy. But I guess the idea of the
kind of private mental states.
You probably do get somewhere by
uh accounting for its evolutionary past,
right? In the same way that I get
somewhere from distinguishing myself
from an ant because
well, we have very different pasts and
we've and that evolution is somewhere.
I'm not saying entirely, but in some
ways guiding that which, you know, the
affordances which the landscape presents
to us.
But no, I I So so if we then go back to
actually what you do say, your your sort
of positive account I can give a quote
here. Um I thought this was really
great. So
st-
um so you've got sort of yeah, your your
structural resemblance and how we're
going to get representation out of that.
And you say that um
the s- problem can be solved by
requiring that the structural
resemblance can be used or exploited by
a cognitive system in order to make
cognitive functioning effective.
Um this captures the intuitive idea that
a representation, mental or otherwise,
serves as a proxy or stand-in for what
is
what is represented. And I certainly
see that
in the sense of how you would then get
representations cuz in the sense it's
it's meaningful the organism.
Some evolutionary biologists might go,
"Well,
that just, you know, what makes
something is effective is its evolution,
you know, its evolutionary payoffs."
I'm still struggling, at least from
that, to see the strong divorce
from
teleo-
functionalism or or teleo-semantics.
Is it the addition of the kind of truth
conditions
that
get us away from a purely teleo-semantic
or teleo-functional functional semantic
semantics?
Well, okay. So, I guess I don't see a
deep distinction between an account in
terms of truth conditions and a
teleo-semantic account necessarily.
Okay.
I thought at least
um that what people like Millikan were
trying to do is is provide an account of
how you get from
um
very naturalistically um
understandable things like
states carrying information about other
states to
uh and things like natural selection to
an account of
representational content. And the main
ingredient that's missing there is the
possibility of error.
Um and I think of those as sort of one
and the same, right? So, the uh the
truth condition of a representation is
what would have to be the case for it to
be accurate or true. And uh you know, so
if you're if you provide an account of
uh error, then in a sense you provided
an account of something that can
function as a truth condition.
Mhm.
But, I think
I I guess I just don't see. So, I think
you do need some account, some some some
account of the possibility of
of error. Um so,
we did discuss uh some ways that you
might get error out in that
paper that you're quoting from, I I
think. Um so, you could have you could
have an accurate generative model that
is it's it's structure
resembles the structure of the
generative process in relevant ways,
but it could be misregistered. So you
could you know, you could infer that
you're in some state that you're not
because of either because of
misapplication of the model or just
because hey, it's a probabilistic model
and
Yeah.
sometimes well, what's probable isn't
what's actual.
Right. Right.
So so there's
that's that's one way of of explaining
it. Um,
in general I think you can also just
look at the broader even just
it's a bit of a cartoon to say
completely synchronously because any
process is somewhat temporally extended.
So I would say history matters only to
the extent that you're trying to give an
account of a process that might exist in
some time scale. And so from the point
of view of a smaller time scale that
might be a historical matter. But I
don't think you need you should for
example, you shouldn't have to go
deep or at all into evolutionary history
I think to give an account of my current
perceptual ability.
That is to give an account of the fact
that I can perceive things and that I
have mental states with contents. You do
have to appeal to evolution to explain
or or it's it's at least a very good
theory if you want to explain like well,
how did I get
into the
the state in which I have this capacity.
But I just think those are two different
questions. Um,
So I don't think I've really I really
answered your question yet, but so I
think if you just look at the roughly
synchronous
um,
you know, present day organization of
the organism you should be able to tell
what's Now, this is is this is sort of
idealizing. I don't think you can
actually do this practically speaking in
in every case, right? Um, you you need
to have like a if you could take a
snapshot of my physical organization
right now and it might take months or
years of analyzing it to figure out what
the actual functional profile of all of
the components of me as a physical
system is or are um
if you could do that I think you could
tell a story about like well what's the
what what is the
what is the current functional role of
this thing say it's a it's a belief that
you know uh
a belief that there's a fence across the
street um
and
you could give an account of the content
in those terms in terms of like well
which aspect of the generative process
does this aspect of the generative model
map onto
um and yet it could still be the case
you could independently investigate
whether there is in fact a fence across
the street and you could say well
this representation has that content but
he's wrong about that aspect of the
world
Right. Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. No,
you're absolutely right. Of course you
you you'd certainly make a point of
misrepresentation. This is for those
wondering this is representation in the
prediction error minimization framework
by yourself and Yacob. Um
Yeah, I think another point that you
made there which is important is that
pure functional semantics don't require
this structural mapping.
I think that's important as well that
you don't necessarily need this
relationship between something like a
generative process and a generative
model in traditional teleosemantics. Um
another thing that you add that I
thought was really interesting I'd love
to
learn about and sort of peruse is this
idea of content holism.
Um cuz that's a kind of additional part
to your proposal.
And you say here the content of one part
of the overall representation depends on
the structure of the whole and thus
cannot be determined without
simultaneously fixing the content of the
other parts. And you also I should point
out in a footnote I believe allow for
that to become recursive. So that's not
you know the the part is not just the
part it might also be the whole for a
sub components.
How what what is content holism? How did
you come to that idea and what does it
add to your
structural representationism.
Right. So, I recently was talking with
some philosophers who are fellow
graduates from my philosophy PhD program
at the CUNY Graduate Center. And I
um I tend to just like assume that
everyone
thinks in terms of um you know, content
holism and stuff. And they were like,
"No, if you're going to submit a paper
on this stuff, you really have to
explain that cuz like people don't think
about that."
So, I realized, okay, that's something
that has to be unpacked. So,
um
I This is something that I got, I'd say
um primarily from from Quine, from the
philosopher W. V. Quine, who was um
So, my my PhD supervisor David Rosenthal
was heavily influenced by Quine and
Sellars, and they're both uh
both theorists who think along these
lines. I think this is one of the great
divides in like philosophical
discussions about semantics. Um
you know, in the past past century. I
would just say that um
I don't see holism as something that I'm
adding to the package. It's not like
something that I'm sort of tagging on to
the view. I think pretty much any
functional
role type of semantics, which I take
structural resemblance theories to be in
a species of, um
is has to have this feature. So, um if
you're if the if the if the view is that
your generative model gets its content
in virtue of resembling the generative
process,
um and by the way, when I just to make
this clear cuz this this also has come
up in some discussions with people like
um at least when I when I think about
that, uh I think of the generative model
as something that has dynamics and
itself unfolds over time.
Right? So, you so you have a sort of
four-dimensional, if you will, um thing
that resembles a four-dimensional
external thing or
Right. Right.
that might happen to be externally real
as well.
If you're lucky and if your model's
accurate. Um
And if And if we're not solipsists.
And if yes, and if anything exists.
Sorry. Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah. Yeah, so, um
um
Right. So,
the
um
So, the structural Right. So, so
if you want to understand how anything
in that model, so so obviously
generative models are and generative
processes are complex things. Um Do you
want to understand the content of any
particular mental state, say, and let's
say it's realized by some pattern of
activity in prefrontal cortex or
whatever,
you need to understand how it What role
does that play in my overall model, this
four-dimensional object? And then,
what analogous role does something play
in in the system I'm representing? And I
I just To me, that seems like from the
ground up it's going to be a holistic
account because the content of this
structure
really depends on the role it plays in
the whole.
Right. Right. I guess uh where I'm where
I probably need clarification is the
idea that part-part relations
as you say, themselves are not
resemblance relations.
And then folding that into the footnote,
which is that the parts can also
function as structural representations
in these hierarchically organized
systems. I guess I don't So, if the
content is fixed
according to its representation the
structural representation as a whole,
and thus it doesn't get its content just
purely by the part that it plays, but
actually well, to sit here the
individual part that plays but actually
the fact that it's integrated in the
whole.
And yet, it can also constitute a whole
within, let's say, a smaller macro
blanket, if you will.
Um
Those two
Can we hold both of those up at the same
in the at the same time?
Um
I think so. I'm glad you're talking
about the footnotes, by the way. I love
my footnotes. I would have footnotes
within footnotes if I could.
Footnotes are very important. Footnotes
People People ignore them. I love
footnotes.
Yeah. They're ter- They're terrible for
readers, but
anyway.
They're useful for writers, yeah.
Yeah, yeah. So, I guess I don't see any
any um conflict here. So,
um
for example, say some some cortical mini
column has a plays a particular role
with respect to your to one's entire
brain, where it really represents
I don't know the the
the
location or the pose of some object. And
And when I say represents that, I mean
the role that this mini column plays in
the overall system is analogous to the
role that object plays
in the relationships among things in the
in the represented system. Right? So,
that's that's the basic structural
resemblance relation. Um then that
that mini column might also have its
internal structure
um
in virtue of which it represents
something.
But, I think we're talking about two
different levels of description,
possibly two different in a in a
multi-scale active inference picture,
those might be two different agents.
Yep. Yep.
And whether I really want to attribute
agency to mini columns and cortical mini
columns, I don't know, but like
Sure.
the point is it would be
this this subsystem that would have its
own um structural representationally
grounded content would be a distinct
thing that would just be a part of this
larger system, which is me, and
only insofar as that thing played the
role it does in my generative model
would it have content would it
constitute part of my point of view of
the world.
Yes. So, okay. So, maybe I can
articulate a bit better. I guess my
question here is
well, one is a kind of more pragmatic
question is about like sort of where do
we cap off the structured representation
as a whole? Like that you know, where do
I end in some sense? But, we can leave
we can park that for 1 second.
I guess my point is you say
structured representation as a whole
gets its content by resemblance, the
same need not be true of its parts.
These get their content via the overall
structural resemblance, but the
part-part relations themselves are not
resemblance relations.
So,
the let's let's say the content of the
the component part
gets it you know gets it gets that
content because of the overall
structural resemblance. But my problem
here is okay, I of course I can grant
you that and
that works for me, but the problem would
be then embedding that in a hierarchy
where you say that that part itself
constitutes a holistic structure.
Whose
because you say um
we do not mean to rule out that parts
may also be structured and function
themselves as structural
representations.
Right?
Yeah.
So, but then that has its own holistic
identity.
Yeah? Because it's it by you know
by which the its component parts form
their identity according to this model.
So, I guess I'm just I can imagine there
is a way out, but I guess I'm slightly
confused about how something can't have
its content fixed
unless it is part of a structured whole
and yet is providing a kind of
structured whole for
subparts unless
those subparts in some ways are also
contingent on the overall structured
whole and we just have a hierarchy of
identity or meaning.
So,
yeah. So, so my current understanding of
this I think it would be great if it
would be really cool if you could cash
out the content. So, let's say I have a
generative model, whatever it
constitutes it, some internal structures
I would say. Um
if we could
if we could sort of show what the
internal relationships are between that
model
and lower scale models of individual
neurons for example such that the
contents
Let's Let's say experience. Look, I'm
not attributing consciousness to neurons
necessarily. I think we could say we
could leave You can divorce
consciousness from representational
content to some extent, even if you're
an internalist, right? I'm I still think
you could talk about uh maybe this is
part of my deep um the way
idiosyncrasies of the way I was trained
in philosophy, but I'm comfortable
thinking about
you know, unconscious thoughts at the
personal level and such. So, I don't
think I think you can talk about the
content of
uh in
uh of my states divorcing it somewhat
from consciousness. So,
we we It would be really cool if like
the content of my current thought had
some intrinsic relationship to the
content of the thoughts of the neurons,
right? But, I don't see that that has to
be the case, and that's my my answer to
you is just
um
whatever lower-level structure it is.
And so, yeah, again, this structure
could play a role in my the overall
structure. Let's just say it's my
central nervous system that's the
relevant vehicle. I don't know if that's
what it is. But, say it's that.
It would be in virtue of the This thing
would be basically an atom in a sense
with respect to that level of
description.
Right? All that would matter would be
And this this is definitely consistent
with the hierarchical active inference
point of view. What would matter would
be its Markov blanket, right? Its
internal states can't matter
functionally to the system at that
level.
Right.
Cuz any internal states that produce the
same input-output profile, the same
interface would would do just as well.
Um Nevertheless, that thing might be a
whole whose parts
um
map onto the parts of some external
things.
Right?
Mhm.
Uh it's just that that would be a a
different system. That would be like a
system at a lower level. And so, it the
content I I guess one one upshot of
holism, it's a bit of a of a hermeneutic
type of picture where the content um is
sort of relative to the or it's it's
associated with the system that you're
describing. And so, the fact that this
thing is a holistic vehicle for content,
um,
isn't inconsistent with its being just a
part at the higher level because those
are two different, um, sort of content
descriptions, right? Content sub Alex
and content sub
uh,
cortical column or whatever.
Mhm. Mhm.
You seem very unsatisfied with that.
No, I'm not. I'm not. I'm not. I'm not
unsatisfied. It's It's
just a broader point. It's kind of
difficult to do these things in real
time in conversation, you know, you need
to sit down and draw something or have
some time to think about it.
We can park that. We can come back to
it. We can We can park it. It's a It's a
fascinating idea. And I think it's also
really important for active inference
generally, um, and predictive coding
because
you can have this kind of very
coarse-grained
idea of a hierarchy whereby the top
parts contextualize, constrain,
determine the lower parts.
But that kind of once you get into the
granular level
and the philosophically rather vague
point, which is
you know, priority you know,
significance hierarchy priority is a
spectrum and what you know, at what
point we can cast these strict
divisions,
then I think these questions start to
matter, which is about these part-whole
relations,
um, which actually leads me very nicely
into predictive coding. Um, so, yeah,
predictive coding in some ways
comes along with active inference and
the Bayesian brain hypothesis. I think
people have
started to be a bit more strict about
distinguishing sort of continuous state
space, discrete discrete state space,
and Pompey P schema, and predictive
processing. But, predictive coding is
still a very important part of the
literature.
I really really loved your paper where I
got a complete history lesson in
predictive coding, Helmholtz machines,
uh, Jeff Hinton. I just I thought it was
great. Um
and people hear
these
words and terms thrown around like
Helmholtz machine, generative model,
discriminative model, recognition model,
and they they probably don't know what
it means. Uh and in a sense they they're
relying on an authority like you to hold
the meaning. Um
So, I thought we could kind of unpick
that, not only for the audience but also
for myself. Um because I take some of
these things just as historical fact.
So, perhaps we can start with the
distinction between a generative model,
a discriminative model, and a
recognition model.
Sure. Um
So, with the caveat that I am also this
is also for me because refreshing one's
own
memory is always a good thing.
Sure.
So, I'd say let's start with generative
versus discriminative discriminative
model. Um so, this is within I'm already
assuming that we're talking about
probabilistic models here.
Um so, a generative model is just
basically a joint probability density
over some variables of interest, right?
Um a discriminative model uh if you were
going to try to cash that out as like a
um in probabilistic in terms of
probability distributions would would be
a conditional distribution, right? So,
if you have some input X um and some
label Y,
um this model would be a model of the
probability of Y given X, right? And so,
you can use this to
um
you know, these things are typically
used in I guess discriminative types of
of tasks like labeling images or
something, uh classification.
Um
Generative models are just much nicer
and more powerful in many ways. I think
there's all sorts of I don't I don't
need to rehearse all the all the
arguments in favor of them,
No, don't. You don't need to. Don't
worry.
So,
in a from a generative perspective,
instead of so, discriminative model of
um like used use classification might
give you Yeah, the prob- What's the
probability of the label cat given this
input image? Whereas you could instead
set up a generative model that jointly
models um What's What's the What's the
joint probability of labels X and images
Y? And it could be based on some
conditional um some latent variable. Um
and then you would just invert that
model given
You can And it's the nice thing about
paradigms like this and predictive
coding architectures are very good at
this. You can You can supply an image
and invert the model and get and get
predicted label or you can supply a
label and predict an image. So on.
And this And this takes us into the
recognition model. Um People might be
familiar with the idea of a recognition
density.
But maybe not a recognition model as the
inversion of a generative model.
Yeah, so this is something where I need
to um if I'm too if I play too loose and
fast with this distinction, then people
like Carl and Maxwell will take me to
task for it. So
This is one This is one thing that that
has come more clearly into focus for me
over the years, which is that um So the
Helmholtz machine This This was my my
introduction to all this stuff sort of
computationally was was just coding up
one of those and trying it out and um
Sure.
and and learning about its properties.
Um
And so in that model you have an an
amortized like a a learned sort of
frozen recognition model, which is
basically it's your It's your It's your
um trained model for inverting the
generative model. And so by inverting
the generative model, of course, I just
mean
um
given some input, uh you want to infer
some latent state
that that represents the the hidden
state that would have caused that input.
Yeah.
Um
So uh you know, obviously doing that in
general is intractable using naive
Bayesian inference. So you need You want
some
You want to use for example variational
inference. Uh great. So the a Q
distribution, which is your approximate
posterior. And And recognition model uh
in the Helmholtz machine is just a
trained amortized um
par- parameterization of the recognition
density. So, like you give it some
input, you have a set of bottom-up
weights that are can be that can be
distinct from the generative weights
that just map into the latent space.
So, that's your recognition model cuz
it's used for recognition.
Yes.
And
Yeah. And so, from a broader predictive
coding cognitive scientific perspective,
you might want to say, "Well,
clearly organisms like us implement some
form of recognition model." Let's
on the Bayesian brain hypothesis, right?
Let's say we have generative models that
go from like things like concepts to
arrays of of simulated sensory data. You
need some way of getting from the actual
data you receive to the concept back to
the concepts. Um and so, you can think
of that as in a in a broad sense a
recognition model. The reason I said I
have to be careful here is that
you don't need a
amortized mapping in order to do this in
predictive coding architectures. You can
just run the thing
um and do iterative inference.
Yeah.
Um just try to minimize the free energy
over all of the nodes in the network
given an input. And so, you have a
recognition process without necessarily
having um a pre-trained uh recognition
model.
Right, because the Helmholtz machine has
its learning happens in this kind of uh
so-called wake-sleep cycle, right?
Um
which I think some people have have
linked to human sleep, but I won't I
won't go there. Um
I guess I guess a point of confusion for
me. Now, I'm not a computer scientist, a
coder, etc. So, you are going to have to
be patient with me. Um
is the generative model is talking about
these probability densities. Let's say
just over two variables.
Um
now, that seems to me that it doesn't
necessarily prioritize one variable over
the other like a discriminative model
would.
Which sounds to me that then inverting
it doesn't really make sense because you
haven't got a starting version.
So, is the generative model when we talk
about a generative model in
uh uh
predictive coding or active inference,
the probability let's say the
probability of a state uh or well, the
probability of an observation given a
state, let's say. That sounds more
like that very, you know, the line in
Bayes' formula sounds like given your
explanation like a discriminative model.
Yeah, so thanks for the opportunity for
a clar- to clarify this. So,
um
yeah, so in a discriminative model, I I
paradigm for this is like some
feedforward neural network where you've
got
image layer as input
and n layers of processing and like
label layer as output.
If I were to try to train a a Helmholtz
machine, for example, to do that
instead, I would have
image and label
sort of concat- concatenated or you can
think of them as two distinct
modalities, whatever. You'd have these
on the bottom layer and you'd build
whatever
however many layers you want on top of
that. Um and so when I talk about
inverting a generative model,
so I kind of implicitly assume that the
generative model uh has um latent
variables in it.
And so the latent variable, it's often
called like Z or H or whatever, right?
So, you you supply your input, you do
some inference onto this latent
variable,
right? And that's that's your
that's your right, internal representat-
that's your that's your internal states
in an active inference idiom that would
represent the external states, the
hidden external states.
Uh and so
it so both the things that So, instead
of a mapping from the one Let's think of
labels and images as two observation
modalities, right? Instead of Instead of
constructing a mapping directly from one
observation modality to another, in this
kind of model, you would have a mapping
jointly from the observation modalities
to this hidden latent variable.
And inverting the generative model is
inferring the latent variable given the
observations.
I see. So, it's kind of embedded in the
way. Um
it's kind of you're you're get you're
you're discriminating something but
within that that itself is overarching a
the generative relation. Does that make
sense?
Yeah, yes, exactly. So, you could do
discrimination, right? Um you can always
get these conditional distributions from
the joint distribution. So, it was just
a this is a way of That's That's what's
great about generative models. They do
more. I mean, of course, they're also
harder to train. They need, you know,
it's more information that you need to
model. But, if you have one, then you
can do discrimination um by clamping a
label, say, inferring a latent state,
and then generating the other modality.
Cool. Excellent. Um
Yes. Okay, perfect. So,
the the Helmholtz machine is what, 1995,
1996?
And then Friston's predictive coding, I
think, was introduced first in 2005, but
there were probably hints of it earlier
than that. Um
what are the differences between the
two?
Um
Actually, I'm not going to pit
Mr. Dayan over Mr. Friston. So, I'm
going to leave it I'm going to I'm not
going to try and ask for a comparison.
Let's just ask for the the differences
between the two cuz people probably hear
them aligned but don't know how they're
distinguished.
Yeah, yeah. I mean,
I I think a lot of this stuff I I think
Carl and others were working on these
ideas and I think a lot 90s were just
there's amazing stuff going on in
general.
But, anyway, uh
so, yeah. So,
uh one one difference I already
mentioned is that um in the Helmholtz
machine,
you explicitly are training a bottom-up
recognition model. And as you said, this
is usually well, originally
first proposal for this was the
wake-sleep algorithm, where basically
you would
you you present an input,
propagate the activities given the
current weights, and then train the
generative weights to be more likely to
generate that. Then, you would generate
a fantasy top-down, and retrain the
train the recognition weights to
to produce that when you get an input.
Um and it's a way of bootstrapping um,
two models at once. So, the the
generative model and the recognition
model. Um, later on, and I I don't know
as much about this, but um, in
discussing this with colleagues, um,
it's come to light that um,
something that worked better was to just
was to just always um, just always use
the bottom-up activities to train both
models. So, this is called the
re-weighted wake-sleep algorithm. So,
that's that's a tangent. Don't need to
get into that, but um, the the
wake-sleep the Helmholtz machine didn't
work all that amazingly. It was just an
It was an amazing proof of concept. I
always thought of it as like a minimal
mind. Um, cuz it had all the basic
ingredients you need, sort of
imagination, perception, and so on.
Maybe not action, but we can
do that as well.
Um, but so so that's that's one big
difference. Whereas in a predictive
coding network, um,
you've got some vector of um, current
hidden state activities. Um, you get an
input. Uh, you make a prediction or you
you send you send a signal up um, to the
to the hidden layer. Um,
this is the prediction error.
Um, and the prediction error is computed
with respect to the current activity.
And you
you update the activities so as to
minimize the the energy term, right?
Which just which is just additive across
all the nodes.
Um, so you don't there's no recognition
model. Um, you can just use the uh,
you can just use the same the generative
weights. Um, you just just use the
inverse of those to to map to the hidden
state.
Um, and so you're not training two
distinct models. You just train the If
you're training a model like this, you
would just train the
um, you would just train the generative
model by minimizing prediction error.
Um,
other differences, um,
so in the Helmholtz machine, there isn't
really any
uh, there's a certain um, abstraction at
work in that architecture, which is that
although
so I always intuitively thought of this
as as um, modeling the fact that, you
know, we know from from neuroscience
that the same neural hardware is used
for perception and imagination, right?
At least largely.
Overlap. Um, and so, the Helmholtz
machine sort of models that because you
use the same
units, the same artificial neurons to do
the bottom-up sweep as well as the
top-down sweep. Um, but those two
information flows never interact, right?
You've got a wake phase and a sleep
phase, and when you're running the model
in generative mode, you only use the
top-down information. And so, the
authors, um, Hinton and Dayan and all
pointed out that this is not really
ideal as a model of perception because
we know that there are top-down effects
during perception.
Yep.
So, you don't really want just a a
frozen amortized mapping, um, that
propagates forward. You want to use the
top-down information during perception.
And so, predictive coding has that
feature.
So, if you could just clamp a
bottom-level feature vector, whatever
wherever the input is, and the the the
um, the predictive coding algorithm
uh, will be integrating
information from the priors, like sort
of online,
in order to perform the bottom-up
inference in in effect, right? So,
you've got Oh, you've always got
predictions coming down from the top and
prediction error coming up from the
bottom, and these two sources of
information are integrated online during
perception.
So,
it's a much better model in that
respect.
Maybe we can also feed in this idea of,
um, horizontality
in predictive coding. Um, I actually
came to this through Andy Clark's paper
as well, uh, whatever next, cuz he makes
quite a this you know, he makes quite an
explicit point that it's not just
verticality, it's horizontality.
And almost the horizontality, if I if
I'm not wrong,
is really kind of where the inference is
happening, right? It's it's it's kind of
the selection of the best hypothesis.
So, maybe you could do a better job than
me, uh, and just explain, you know, what
what does horizontal horizontality
introduce to this picture?
So, I don't know if I am sure how uh uh
Mandicark used that word. I assume you
mean like lateral connections and sort
of
Lateral, yes.
No, no, that's it's fine. Uh so,
right. So, definitely there's um
there's well,
so, whether or not you have
lateral connections in your model,
right? There's a there's other ways of
achieving that. You can have
sort of diagonal influences like you you
know, you use
the representations at this layer
propagate
information upward and then there's a
there's a sort of recurrent feedback
loop where
this layer gets modulated again. But,
you in any case, you get this sort of
Mhm. I don't know if it's always
winner-take-all, but sort of
winner-take-all behavior where one of
the hypotheses at this level selected.
You can definitely I I know some of the
earliest predictive coder predictive
coding models were literally
um yeah, we're not even higher level
models. They were just like um to to
model um I guess
efficient information processing in
retinal ganglion cells, I think, where
you'd have like
the receptive So, so, you'd have a
neuron here and it's in it's it's output
it's spiking activity would be modulated
sort of dampened by what was going on in
its in its vicinity.
Well, yeah, yeah, yeah. You made Yeah,
you made that point, I think, in the
paper where you Yes, you talk about the
kind of center
uh I'm butchering this, but yeah, the
and the surround
That's like the early '80s, I think.
Yeah, yeah. So, that was one of the
first applications of predictive coding
was instead of prior information
possibly at a very deep level, right?
From like whatever evolutionary priors
or or cognitive priors, it's just like,
well, we sort of embody the prior that
um
this cell only needs to fire if what
it's doing is is different from what
would be expected given its neighbors.
Yes.
Um so, yeah. And And so, so, and
certainly and and one of I think Carl's
earliest paper on this or one of the
earlier ones I'm familiar with it's it's
called something like a theory of
predictive coding responses
predictive coding responses, thank you.
Um also discussed
them all, not I've read them, I
memorized them.
That's what you got to do. I I need to
um up my game on that.
No, no, no.
So so yeah, he discusses the role of
lateral connections um and sort it's
it's you know, it's it's sort of a
mechanism for competition in a way. It's
a one it's another way of inducing
sparsity, right? So if he's I've played
around with
um versions of a Helmholtz machine. I
don't know what you I don't know what
you call this, but I just added some
lateral connections to the Helmholtz
machine cuz it doesn't have those.
Right. I mean, well, you break certain
theoretical guarantees if you do that.
Um but
but but anyway, um and what happens is,
right, you get a increasingly sparse
representation because of this sort of
competitive um potentially behavior
among the units at one level.
Yeah, yeah, that makes sense.
I guess um
I feel like an issue that I've always
had with predictive coding at a very
very general level, and this is more
definitely more indicative of my
intellectual limitations than the actual
theory's limitations,
is
it's very difficult to uh
be able to say at a snapshot in time
what's going on.
I think over a diachronic diachronically
it kind of makes sense, right? Like I
get these bottom you know, you get these
bottom-up prediction errors, which in
some ways lead to uh model changes at
very you know, much higher levels, but
still those higher levels constrain the
expectations at the lower levels.
But I guess
it's kind of like where it's it's
difficult to picture as happening all at
the same time
because it's
prediction error trickling up, but the
predictions that are going to deal with
those prediction errors are already
coming down, so why are those
predictions errors coming up in the
first place, right? If they should be
getting suppressed by the things that
are coming down.
And maybe some people skirt this problem
just by adopting some kind of linear
time sequence in their minds. I
understand that it's all happening at
the same time, but they go
"Oh, like this this level can't deal
with it, so it goes up, and eventually
you get the prediction, and it
suppresses it." I've always just found
that to be very problematic because who
is saying at which level the prediction
error stops, right? It just seems like
it's a kind of miracle.
So, maybe you can help me, or maybe you
can't help me.
Uh
is this an intellectual Is this an
intellectual limitation of my own, or is
this something that's come to mind
before?
Um yeah, so I I think I can help you to
some extent. Um
I don't know that it's an intellectual
limitation. I think it's
I don't see any problem. I sort of
I tend to think about this stuff
sometimes in a quite visual way. I just
sort of imagine
imagine this stuff working, and then
also you try it out in code, and it
works, so it's like
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Um so, I would like to give you a more
discursive answer though. I think um
Um so, yes, indeed, if you try to So,
and I've I've definitely built models.
Um there's David Heeger has a paper also
on It's a similar title to Karl's paper.
It's a theory of cortical something, uh
where he has a very similar model, and
yeah, so so, in implementing this, it's
like, well,
what do you update first? First of all,
I'm like, how do you right? So, I think
the solution to all that stuff, part of
it is and I thought a bit about how to
how to build predictive coding
architectures is um just do do the
updating asynchronously, which, you
know, if you if you want a little bit of
um background of that, it's basically
like each neuron, each model neuron
would just be its own sort of process,
like So, we can go deeper into the the
computer science stuff if you want, but
like basically each neuron would be
running in its own sort of processor
thread, and it would take inputs and
operate them as it gets them, and then
produce outputs as it as it has them to
produce. And all of this would be going
on simultaneously. So,
the idea that you need to first get all
of the input to it to a layer of the
prediction error and integrate it with
the top-down predictions and figure out
how much information to pass on.
Practice these are just not issues,
right? It's so and even without going
into the implementation of this stuff in
terms of parallel distributed
processing, you can just think about um
the energy function. So, the energy the
the free energy
function that you're trying to
functional that you're trying to
minimize,
um
it's
it it's additive across the nodes. So,
each node locally computes its free
energy. So, whenever it gets an input,
whatever its current state happens to
be,
um
right? You you just you just modulate
its output based on that. Um
So, I guess and I guess I imagine this
happening So, it's it's sort of chaotic,
I suppose, right? The the matter
It's um uh
you would just basically each each each
neuron locally process its its own
its own input and produce an output and
and then,
you know, if you're simulating this on a
serial system, you have to choose when
to do what.
Right.
Um but that's not terribly central, I
think, to the architecture.
Yes, I guess I guess the problem there
is
if every neuron is just doing its own
thing and over time, you know, over time
over the sequence of neuronal activity,
prediction error just gets sliced off,
right? And so, you get this additive
minimization of free energy.
You can run a kind of philosophical
thought experiment and just go, "Well,
what happens if the total, you know,
amalgamation or accumulation of all the
neurons relevant to this activity just
they don't do they just don't they just
can't get rid of all that prediction
error?"
But we're we're we're siphoning off
learning, right? So, we're siphoning off
uh parametric updating because we're
saying that's happening asynchronously.
I'm just left with a bundle of
prediction error.
And you never hear in the you know, you
always hear well, that's just going to
end up getting minimized. So,
But
Yeah, so so I mean
So, it's not your prediction error is
never minimized, right? If it were
minimized minimized in the sense of like
Life would be over.
You would be dead, yeah. Um so,
you know, there's always
Mhm.
It's an interesting question you bring
up like what what if there's just
prediction error that can't be handled?
Is it just going to be this oscillating
like, you know, chaotic system where the
prediction error just bounces around?
Yes. Like that's what would happen.
Right? You you would just you you just
shunt around the prediction error and
you'd have the sort of I mean I've seen
this happen in in models, right? Where
like you just it just doesn't converge,
right? You just sort of you just you
just can't
there's no it's not a stable state. It's
maybe a maybe a um metastable state or
something, right? Where where
um there's or there's oscillatory
behavior or something. Um
which Carl would say is is important,
right? On to to life on larger time
scales.
Yes.
Um
solenoidal flows.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, everything is
always sort of smooth. So, it's it's
it's pathological if you ever get a
probability of a one or zero.
Um in these models and I'd say in real
life as well.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There might be exceptions like there
might be some
We can get this we go straight into like
crazy amounts of mysticism. Maybe
there's some kind of prior of one of
like existence or something. But like
I hope so.
I think so. I think so, actually. But
yes, in in
terms of the probabilities that are
represented by your model, like it's
it's it's never going to be no
prediction error.
No, Carl has a valid point. And I guess
once you fold in the
the the learning, whether that's
parametric learning or structure
learning,
you know, that prediction error that was
so grave at one point is eventually
going to get resolved one way or another
whether that's through
um
You know,
I find sometimes when I run into this
problem just anecdotally, I find myself
going towards a variational free energy
for equation. Just being like, "There's
my You know, there's my safety." Because
through either action or perception,
we're minimizing you know, we're we're
going down those descents of free
energy. Okay, you you've you've you've
sort of you've quashed my anxiety
somewhat. Um
one other sticking point I have with
active inference.
And this really came to light actually a
couple of weeks ago when I spoke to
Ronald Sadtler who's a neuroscientist at
University of Vienna and he's wrote and
he's written It's not a word. He's
written about the amygdala from an
active inference perspective. And he
does this really nice thing of
distinguishing between kind of I think
he calls them preference priors, you can
call them phenotypic priors,
evolutionary priors, whatever you call
them. But prior preferences.
And then also what I've been calling
state priors. Right? So, literally, what
state do I expect to be in now?
Right? And you can have that as your D
matrix or your B matrix if we're doing
pom DP schema.
And then also and that obviously feeds
into perceptual updating just on like
some if we have just like naive Bayes. I
know it's not happening like that, but
let's just say.
But then you also have these preference
priors.
Right? In many ways, as Karl has made
very explicit, like that too is shaping
your perception, right? Hence why we
have visual illusions.
I just find in the literature there
hasn't been too much work gone into
distinguishing those and also talking
about that interplay.
For you, does that just come out in a
hierarchical system? Do Do those things
converge on being the same thing? We
just call them a prior. Or is it useful
to continue to distinguish them?
Yeah, that's a great question. I mean,
ideally for me it's the
um
I guess the former. It's it's that they
come out to be the same thing.
Um so, if If doing pom DP modeling, of
course, yes, you'll define like a C
vector, which is your preference, and
then you'll you might also have um
you well, you'll have a you'll also have
a D a D vector and so on. But, I think
ideally in a hierarchical system, it
should be that the
these are just you just have your
priors. And to me, what the what the
phenotypic um
distribution is or the the the deep sort
of priors that represent desires and,
you know, homeostatic um requirements,
to me, that's just when you're your
whole hierarchy links into the something
at that's sort of at the root node of
this this of this um graph, right? So,
you have like a basic need for food,
let's say.
That's not going to change, right? You
can't really rewrite that or learn it
learn your your way out of it. Um and
then what's going what you're modeling
at the lower levels could very well be a
consist a situation that's not
consistent with that prior being
satisfied. Um
but they're still just priors, right?
And really what you want is that the
priors at that deep level, which are
constitutive of and defining of the kind
of thing you are,
you want those to
smoothly propagate to the periphery and
for everything to work out well. But, of
course,
what you're currently representing at
the lower levels of of a hierarchy
internal hierarchy is going to be the
result of variational inference,
right? So, I think of I mean, there's
some talk about this in the later
sections of that paper that Maxwell and
Ryan Smith and I wrote on beliefs and
desires.
Where
it basically the Q distribution is your
so so your beliefs in in the bare-bones
version of the picture, um yeah, you're
that's that's your estimate of the
current state of the world. It might be
arbitrarily different in principle from
your desires. Um but, still
um yeah, and the and the priors the
priors are just the the generative model
itself, that's uh the joint distribution
that defines the kind of thing that you
are. Um so, I think that
said a lot, but I I think basically the
the distinction between two parameters C
and and D in a hierarchical model, which
is
in a way that you might set some of
these these priors, I think that that's
more of a modeling convenience than
anything. So, I'm not sure that everyone
would agree with me on that, but
It's it's really interesting. Uh,
it's really useful explanation. I mean,
yeah, once you have them in a kind of
smooth hierarchy, you can start to kind
of visually or mathematically see how it
might all sync up.
I guess the issue is in folk psychology
we we still there's an intuition always
that beliefs,
preferences, let's say, uh, sorry,
desires, preferences are distinct from
my beliefs about the what's going on in
the world right now. And I guess that's
held in some sense
uh, because there's a hierarchy.
It It is, yeah. I would I would say that
Yeah.
Sorry, I
wouldn't say that this
eradicates the distinction.
I I understand the the the pull towards
that and this and like some of Andy
Clark's uh, work where he's
um,
I don't I think he's
he's it's not clear that he wants to
preserve this this sort of classical
distinction between beliefs and
priors in a way.
Um,
so I understand the pull towards that,
but I do think
even though your your desires are these
priors, which are belief-like in a way,
as they
to me they're they're really not, right?
So, the the prior the priors are
Right. Okay. So, the priors are
certainly They they have they represent
something, right? And so, they have you
know, if they're desires, then in the
classical philosophy mind way of putting
it, they have satisfaction conditions,
right?
Uh, which are a lot like truth
conditions. It's just that it's a
different propositional attitude. So,
um,
you know, they're they're in the same
the representation-wise they're in the
same format. It's a different attitude
to the same kind of content. And then
the result of posterior inference is a
belief. And so, the same
structure, cognitive or otherwise, I
tend to I tend to think that there's a
very transparent relationship between
cognitive and physical sort of
implementation structures.
Anyway, the structure
can, as considered as opposed to the
results of posterior inference, it's a
belief.
Um but then considered uh in terms of
its downstream effects in a in a
top-down generative model, it sort of
functions as a desire.
So, you have both things in the system.
Yeah.
They're entangled.
Yeah. I mean, I wonder whether how
Yeah, so you the hierarchy is a is a
really useful
way in which that I guess again
philosophically vague distinction can be
made concrete.
And obviously, people also talk about
the temporality aspect of the generative
hierarchy in so far as the higher levels
track slower fluctuations in the
external dynamics and
the lower levels the faster dynamics.
It makes one think whether
that it that necessarily maps onto
desires, preferences, and so on
only being at the higher level that
I.E.
being the result of slower fluctuations,
right? Like I had ice cream. I've had
ice cream a thousand times. I like ice
cream
versus a belief that there is ice cream
or that there isn't ice cream.
It's an interesting question. It's an
interesting question whether beliefs uh
sorry, well, desires, let's say,
necessarily
need to originate at the higher level
and whether sort of more classical folk
psychology beliefs are lower level.
Ooh, can I jump in on that?
Please. No, no, no, I wasn't just
spitballing. Yeah, please. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, go.
I I really like that. So, I think I
think Andy Clark also talks about this
in one of his recent papers uh more
recent papers. So,
there's a sense in which you really can
talk about sort of like false desire and
versus more genuine desire that really
stems from your being in that I I think
sort of genuine sources of desires
are from the deepest levels of the
model, but then in cases of like
addiction
what gets happens is
Yes.
Right. So So basically there's a
bottom-up sort of an attractor sort of
manages to establish itself in your
system on the basis of bottom-up input
that creates a a sharp expectation over
a particular outcome
that might be not at all a good fit with
your deeper priors, but that just gets
self-confirmed so much that it becomes a
rigid feature of the model. And so
that's the I think that's a perfectly
possible um active inference account of
um of addiction. Yeah, and there's a
desire there that will in that it
motivates your behavior and you will go
for the thing, but uh it's definitely
deeply obviously um it it impoverishes
the rest of the model and
Right.
Well, that's really nice. Yeah, that's
really really nice. Um John Vervaeke is
a very, you know, big hero of mine.
Talks about reciprocal narrowing and
reciprocal opening
with respect to addiction. I think this
isn't his direct work. I can't remember
whose it is, but the idea being that as
you say
addiction is a kind of downward spiral
such that and you can just think about
it in terms of dopamine. Um such that a
singular source becomes your kind of
source of pleasure in the very first
psychology way, but also like your
singular prior and everything becomes
determined by that. And maybe what he
he, you know, he will use the word like
agape, but you know, you have this kind
of opening. Uh maybe Heidegger would
call it aletheia, where you have this
kind of disclosure and that actually
opens yourself up to the world.
And I guess yeah, maybe it is a bit
mystical, but I wonder whether it in
doing that we're uncovering something
which is actually
was already there in the way.
I absolutely I think I think the sort of
the
Sure, there's a there's a mystical take
on that, but it's it's also just um
absolutely the case that you want you
want as much variability in your states
as as is consistent with preserving the
phenotype and so
Yep. Yep.
that's something that for example we've
written up uh Mao and Maxwell and and um
um ready it and others have written in
that resilience uh the work on
resilience
Yes, uh Mark Miller and yeah.
Yeah, Mark Miller yes, thank you. Um
I've been doing a lot of things so I
haven't thought about that paper in a
while but uh
but yes, like and then that's just comes
out of just very I think just
variational inference even like you just
you just want to maximize the the
entropy of your distribution subject to
the constraints from your model.
And yeah, Ryan who you mentioned earlier
he sort of has this idea of um
structure learning aiding emotional
granularity and that being really useful
because you don't get trapped into
thinking that you're furious if you're
actually maybe just a bit frustrated or
and and and so on. It's all uh
complexity minus accuracy at the end of
the day.
Um
yeah, I don't know what I've had this
idea and I'm thinking maybe writing a
paper on that but I've
there's I think a really nice addition
to this whole picture is the idea of
selective attention.
Um so Beck Mitra who I think was in
Carl's lab back in the day, he wrote a
bunch of papers with Carl about
attention and he has this 2019 paper
about selective attention. I've spoken
about it on the podcast before.
And the idea being that your
priors, your preferences constrain your
attention. And that kind of make that's
very sort of in sync with traditional um
bias competition theory. Right? And
stuff that I wrote about during my
masters. The idea being that you know
what is
elevated in terms of gain control aligns
with is actually in line with your
goals. So if I'm looking for a ginger
person then all the templates of things
that are orange or ginger stand out to
me.
And I've been having this idea that we
can actually root that selective
attention
to the very deepest level of our belief
hierarchy
such that we kind of do have it's very
Jordan Peterson actually cuz it's very
sort of narratively, but we do have
these kinds of deep like what like we
have have basically a guiding principle.
And
that could be governed by your biology,
by your by your socio-cultural. But I
really like the idea that like your
value you know, I tweeted that thing
that you liked which was Simone Weil
attention is prayer.
Um
influenced by Iain McGilchrist what
attention is a moral act. And I think
that's really powerful because
attention is basically a
phenomenological indicator of that which
you are guided by.
Mhm. So I'm thinking of maybe again it's
a I'm putting this out there so no one
steals it, but I've got this I'm trying
to think about how to formalize this
idea that like the very deep
temporally invariant parts of our being
might actually be the guiding force of
our attentional schema.
That's that's wonderful. I hope you
write that paper. Um I I haven't done so
much research on attention
as such uh in in the psychological
literature and such. So it's it's it's
really cool to hear that
what you researched confirms this kind
of perspective.
Well, hopefully. Hopefully someone
doesn't come into the comment section.
You know how those comment sections be.
People always have things to say. Um
this might be a slightly selfish
question, uh but I don't think it is
because I think people will also benefit
from this. You say that I wanted to kind
of go back to your
journey as an academic if you will
and starting off as philosophy and then
Andy Clark and then sort of finding
modeling. So what really helped was
actually modeling a Helmholtz machine
for example.
And you hear this a lot, you know, if
you want to learn how to
do pom DP stuff, know how to do the
MATLAB work.
The question I've always had like I
haven't done any of this coding.
What does it look like?
I mean, when you say I code a Helmholtz
machine,
what do you get on your screen? I know
that sounds really stupid, but I think
people are kind of confused about what
that looks like, especially when Carl
talks about "Oh, you get these little
agents who are doing things." What What
does that actually look like?
Yeah, no, I don't It's not a stupid
question. It's It's kind of It's one of
the problems you have to solve if you
want to want to do this stuff, right?
So, So, what I did, I mean, this was in
the relatively early days of this stuff
in in academic in broader academia in
the sense that unless you were doing
machine learning, you
probably didn't usually care about this
stuff. So,
what I did was
I started writing it in JavaScript. I
used dynamic CSS to render this as a web
page.
Mhm.
You know, um I'll have to send you I'll
have to send you some link. I'll post it
on my Twitter or something.
Yeah. Basically, I had this very early
The reason I never shared it so much
with the world at the time is that it
didn't work very well at all. But, I
basically had a Helmholtz machine
visualized in a in a browser and it was
like
you'd just have like um some squares for
each neuron. There'd be some In the
hidden layers, you'd have these sort of
static-y looking patterns as you'd
expect. And then,
you'd visualize the output layer as an
image. And I sort of overlaid the um
the input the ground truth input image
with the prediction using like red and
blue or something. I got the those color
codes come from like Jeff Hinton's work,
and a lot of people have used them. Um
or red and green, maybe. But, anyway, um
so, that to me that I really needed this
concrete visualization to like
understand No, if you run Carl's MATLAB
code, it's much more like you just get
the output. I mean, it's not it's a
That's a fine way of working. It's
worked well for for many people, right?
Like you see the belief distribution
change over time.
Um just sort of plotted on um on an axis
like, you know,
based on various conditions. Um
But, so, yeah, so in other in in any
case, I mean, you I think you you need
to set up um a visualization that makes
this stuff intelligible. I feel like I
don't know if that was the heart of your
question, but you were kind
no. No, no. I'm
Yes. I'm just kind of
I guess people always ask like
What What are these like What are you
know when we talk about in silico
agents?
Right.
Is that a thing like really or is that
just a metaphor?
I mean
I kind of hope it's a metaphor cuz I
just you know
kill them thousands of them a year if if
they're real you know.
Oh yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah sure.
my browser window and it's just gone. Um
but no I mean I think to the extent that
you can model to the extent that you
think these types of models are models
of agency
Mhm.
then yeah it's real. Um it's not
browser window what what do you actually
get? You know what I mean like what what
do you see? When you say agent I think
people naturally think of little gummy
bears or you know little teddy bear
looking things.
Okay. Well so the Homunculus machine
then is a bad example because that's
that's really just doing sort of
um
uh
It was really just showing online
learning of like um
of a generative model and it doesn't
have an action component to be
interesting but um
I've seen tons of visualizations of um
of active inference models and other
similar models. So I mean if you look at
some of the um
some of the machine learning work on
learning to play video games is a good
example. So so
uh
It's a strange case but you know if you
have a
a model that's trained to play Super
Mario Brothers then
I mean you see the effects of the agent
anyway. Um you can you can just visual
It depends on your problem right?
There's plenty of um sort of grid world
type simple proof of concept type active
inference models that get made where you
can see the location of an agent on a
little map or something. Um
I love that.
Yeah. But but typically honestly I mean
just as a as a matter of like everyday
sort of um working reality it's like
usually you'll get a series of plots of
the belief belief updates over time.
Mhm.
Um and the and the action that was
chosen.
Right. And that works.
Yeah and it's an ongoing struggle to
find better, more powerful
visualizations for this stuff.
Sure. Sure. I imagine it is.
Okay.
So, I'm just going
you know, wrapping things up. You've
gone from philosophy to
computational science, let's say.
Um
and the
the the kind of contentious bridge
there, let's say, between phenomenal
structures and mechanical explanations
or mechanical formalisms
is often called the generative passage.
Um
started, I guess, by Varela and then
formalize or, you know, that term
instituted by Maxwell and his team in
that 2022 paper.
I really like that you I think I think I
get this from a lot of philosophers who
start off as philosophers is the kind of
non-reducibility of intentionality, the
non-reducibility of consciousness.
Where What do you think of the
generative passage?
And what do you think is the sort of
most I won't say likely, but the most
adaptive or effective manifestation of
it? And by that, I mean some people talk
about ontological naturalism, which is
we could basically posit as a reductive
approach, and epistemological
naturalism, which is that the way that
we come the way that we think about or
describe, um
let's say, in this case, Bayesian
dynamics is going to be helpful, um or
actually Oh, no, not in that case, it's
not helpful. But it actually does
describe
the structures intentional structures
or a kind of procedural or more,
you know, mechanical way where
it's actually just useful. Like, it's
kind of instrumental. Um but it actually
might not be telling us anything too
concrete about the phenomenal reality.
Now, since you've kind of flirted in
both camps,
where uh
where do your allegiances lie? I don't I
don't mean What What what think?
Yeah, no. Uh so, as far as the
narrowly the term generative passage, um
I stop me if you think I'm misusing that
term. Uh I haven't been deeply involved
in thinking in that term in those terms.
But, I think you're talking about the
relationship between phenomenology and
uh
In this case, Bayesian dynamics, let's
say. Or or
um
You Well, I mean, people talk about
neuro phenomenology, right? So, it could
be neuronal dynamics.
Yeah, yeah, great. So, um yeah, so my
overall So, there's a lot of things
rolled into that question. Um
epistemologically,
I kind of see things as And this is It's
good that you brought this up. I wanted
to comment on this earlier. Um
so, another paper that I haven't
published is on is on this topic. So, um
like I kind of
I would be a transcendental idealist,
except that
the
except that the evidence that I've seen
for that position is empirical. So, I
kind of I the probably someone said
something similar, but I want to I want
to write a paper on the a sort of conte
like almost empirically informed
Kantianism, where it's like, well, what
we've learned about how these systems
work
um
provides evidence for the conclusion
that
the our experience of reality is is
mostly based on
uh prior structures in the brain, right?
Um so, I think that's really interesting
epistemological. It's different from
sort of classical transcendental
idealism, where you just had Kantian
categories, right? Um because you're
you're sort of presuming to say
something it's there's a sense in which
the the the naturalistically studyable
reality comes first there, cuz you're
saying it's like, well, the way neurons
work, we probably encode these
generative models in our brain, right?
And that's why we conclude that um we
have subjective ontologies and such that
we learn in order to parse out the
sensory data.
Um so so overall that's my that's my
sort of
view on the epistemology of it, but um
in terms of the relationship between
phenomenology and cognitive structures
and physical structures,
um I try to in my work I try to um argue
for the the the most minimal account of
that relationship where I where
transparency is the ideal um across all
those levels. So, of course,
that's not going to work perfectly.
Like, if I see a dog on the street, it
doesn't mean there's a dog in my head.
It does mean that there's something
um
it does mean that there's something
whose dynamics reflect the dynamics of
that thing out there. Um if there's a
thing out there, as we said earlier. Um
but but let's for a second let's just
think about the relationship between the
phenomenology and the cognitive
structures, right? Um
um
Uh so yeah, in in the psychophysical
identity paper I also I cite some work
by the Gestalt psychologists who really
assumed that there was a strong
isomorphism there.
Um that you really in a sense if you if
you looked closely enough at the um
well, I I sorry, I was I was shifting to
the physical level of description again.
But certainly that there you should be
able to sort of
re-understand the structure of
phenomenology in terms of um
in terms of the structure of these
Bayesian
prior prior structures basically and
they get updated by by sensory
experience. And so I totally agree with
Maxwell at all on that. The one reason I
haven't been more gung-ho about um
computational phenomenology is just that
I
already assume something further, which
is that like so so their their research
program as I understand it is let's sort
of step back and just try to build a
generative model for phenomenology.
Yep.
And understand
how you can understand phenomenology in
terms of generative modeling.
I think you can just shoot straight
through the cognitive structure and just
talk about isomorphism between the
phenomenological structures
and the cognitive structures the um
implementation bases for those.
Interesting.
so I
I I guess it's good it's epistemically
humble and it's a good project to try to
do that. Um I just find that it's more
effective for me to be constrained by
more
um my theory so I try I I usually when I
think about this stuff I'm constrained
by thinking about neural implementation
level as well as cognitive level as well
as phenomenological.
Oh, so I was hoping you're going to be
looser. Oh, well.
I was hoping you guys
There might be something.
Um
Okay.
I'm joking. You're You're entitled to Of
course you're entitled I I mean I I'm
personally, I mean I've written about
this a little bit publicly.
Uh
Ontologically speaking, I'm quite
agnostic.
Um
I have a I have maybe a slightly
romantic
um constraint which means I just don't
want to do the reductionism. I just
don't. Um
But actually I should clarify I've
actually got the paper up in front of
me. Uh Maxwell and colleagues make it
clear that actually the so-called
ontological naturalization doesn't
necessarily entail reductionism.
Um only so only that and I can quote
here some theoretical framework means
that one reformulates all the
properties, entities, and processes
postulated by that theory in terms of
those posited in the ontology of the
empirical sciences.
Um
And the how that gets then fleshed out
in terms of epistemological
naturalization is that you would take
the core principles and forms of your
explanation from the natural sciences.
And then you would just have
methodological naturalization what I
call procedural naturalization before,
which is bringing your sort of
methodology into continuity with the
empirical sciences. Um so as you say
kind of constraining phenomenology
uh
you know, according to the principles of
psychology and neuroscience without
saying that they are those principles or
without saying that we should only
understand them by those principles.
Um
Yeah, it's a really uh it's a really
nice trifecta that. Um
And I guess there isn't an answer, but
you know, you have some people who are
very adamant that
perhaps even the methodological
naturalization is a step too far. Um and
we should just be as humble as possible
with respect to the nature of
consciousness and
say we we just have no idea in in what
form it's grounded or in what form it
relates to the physical universe. But I
I
I'm probably not that loose.
But no, it's interesting.
Can I follow up with a one more
question?
Please.
Um cuz I I think it's really important
point. Um so I I I don't think in
reductive terms about consciousness.
Like so even if even if it turns out
that there's a perfect isomorphism
between phenomenal, cognitive, and
physical structures,
uh I don't think that means that
everything will be reduced to physical
structures. Like so So I see more I hope
that these lines of inquiry would
converge so that you'd end up seeing
that these are different ways of talking
about the same thing, but it doesn't
mean that one of those ways is
fundamental.
All right.
Um
so
yeah, I don't know if that is any
different than what you just said, but
um
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah. That's absolutely great. Um
okay, final question.
Uh
I should penultimate question.
We can rush through these. Uh
panpsychism.
Is it Is it Is it [ __ ] or is it
brilliant?
Sorry.
We don't
When you put it that way
only cuz you mentioned it. Only cuz you
mentioned it earlier.
No, no, it's certainly not [ __ ] Um
I I don't think it's I don't think it's
brilliant to just rush headlong into it
without thinking about it, but um
no, I think I think it depends what you
mean, right? But like you assume we're
talking about like phenomenal
consciousness,
I'm quite comfortable with the idea that
any physical structure
um
there's some edge cases like rocks where
it's like well
you it's kind of like a don't care case
as Quine would say. It's like
yeah, um it's it's an edge case where
there's no
there's no structure to speak of. I
guess I guess to me the natural view is
that
the kinds of contents you can represent
consciously depend on the complexity of
your structure. But the base ground
existence of sort of a field in which
these things are represented
I don't see why that should be different
from like the basis for physical
existence.
Good.
Final question.
Yeah.
You can only have one for the rest of
I'm being trivial now, but you can only
have one for the rest of your life.
Philosophy, computer science.
Which one are you keeping?
Uh that's rough. Um
I was going to say computer science cuz
I think that the best computer science
contains good philosophy, but I think in
terms of the intention rather than the
extension of these things, I think
philosophy. Cuz you'd end up inventing
computer science if you did philosophy
well enough in the long term.
Fantastic. I'm so glad you said that.
Uh which which one's harder?
Um computer science is way harder.
Is it?
[ __ ] I mean, sorry, if hard means like
it's hard to do, it's like a struggle,
then yes. But if you mean like
Cognitively, theoretically.
Oh, then philosophy.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, we'll have to
discuss more about uh
about all of this stuff.
This was so much fun. Alex, thank you.
Uh thank you for
dealing with my layman thoughts and
terrible attempts at trying to
understand things that are way beyond my
pay grade, but this was awesome.
Likewise. Thanks, Darius. This was this
was great.
Cool. All right. Thank you everyone for
tuning in as well. Okay.